this episode is sponsored by indeed
prime indeed prime helps software
developers simplify their job search and
land their dream job candidates get
immediate exposure to the best tech
companies with just one simple
application - indeed product companies
on Prime's exclusive platform message
candidates with salary and equity up
front
the average software developer gets five
employer contacts and an average salary
offer of $125,000 indeed primes 100%
free for candidates no strings attached
and when you're hired indeed prime gives
you a two thousand dollar bonus to say
thanks for using prod but if you use the
SE radio link you'll get a $5,000 bonus
instead so sign up at indeed.com slash
SE radio
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software yet Levine is the CTO of the
cloud management division at EMC she has
previously worked at several other
companies focused on cloud computing and
virtualization
welcome to software engineering radio
yes it's great to have you so today most
of our software development takes place
on virtualized operating systems what
are the different layers of this virtual
stack oh so so if you're looking today
at all this stock you will see that the
first thing that we have everywhere it's
the hover itself right that's where the
stuff is but the stock is starting and
then you have the drivers of them right
on top of it you have something like an
iPhone either which is supposed to
separate between virtual machines there
then you have the driver the virtual
drivers on the operating system of the
guest then you have the operating system
the kernel of the guest then you will
have their there are their processes
their OS processes that they that their
job is basically to separate between
different processes that running on the
same guest OS and then on top of it
depends you you can put docker container
or any container that you want so that's
what we on top of that and then usually
you're putting all your library and
every complication and everything you
need inside and then you have of course
the application binary and all this
stuff it's it's basically in the end of
the day showing you what you really want
to do which is to run applications so we
have hardware we have Hardware drivers
we have hypervisor virtual hardware
drivers the operating system kernel
there's a bunch more layers why do we
have so many layers
that's a good question that
and I think that the best answer for
that will be evolution right I mean in
the beginning you had only the physical
machines big big computer that I you
know that the business was running like
mainframe they were building they were
buying it it was very very expensive so
then they basically said well that's
very very expensive we need to run more
application on it we cannot run only one
application on this very expensive piece
of physical machine so then basically so
then because of this they will put they
work there is they operate the system
that the job is basically to separate
between users and have to take it right
to make sure that two application can
run on the same machine but then cannot
arm each other or kill the Machine and
then both of the applications will die
but then what happening is that that was
very hot right so people starting to M
you know you need to do time sharing not
the same people you can work on the same
machine at the same time it's very very
complicated so what people wanted to do
is basically they say okay what if we
would take one physical machine and run
one application but again that's in
terms of money it's not really the best
support so then came you know in
evolution they still came and said what
about virtual machines we will put
virtual machine we can actually create
another layer that will separate those
those server will give us the same
ability of actually to run one
application on the server but actually
it will be a several application with
several virtual machine on oneself so
that was the next layer and then after
it you know they said well it's too
complicated there is a lot of
configuration man when you need to do to
this application you need to manage them
very very hard what if you will find a
better way to separate between the
application and on top of the virtual
machine and this is where the container
come basically if the container is a
very good use of that just deploy this
application it's like a packet into if
you like so that when the second when
the last container layer kind of liking
so all this whale is basically just a
pollution but they never kind of like
stop and say well is that make sense or
maybe it's not make sense anymore no one
did that right I basically continue to
be
what exist and so when we when we do
take a step back and we say do we
actually need all of this do we need all
these layers too is there unnecessary
redundancy in this stack what is the
answer to those questions so my opinion
is definitely no there is not I mean I
feel that all those layers of structure
there is a lot of code there is a lot of
dependency a lot of stuff to reason
about and I feel that this is a lot of
unnecessary today we running application
usually want for server sometimes we
running only function right with lambda
and then another another web either
several less application server less
technology that exists today you don't
need all of this it doesn't make any
sense to use it and and and therefore I
think you know I think that the just
overkill and that's what make it's more
complicated less performant ball a lot
of storage that's really really donate
and you still put a bit under by so
basically I really don't think we need
it so the aim of the current stack is
typically to run a single application
with a single user on a single server
how does the aim of the current stack
how does this contrast with how we are
actually building and running
applications when we think about it from
a fundamentals perspective so we are
running eventually one application on
necessarily we are doing it the problem
is that when we're doing it that's the
end result you know this is the
interface that you're putting the
application in the end but there is a
lot of very complicated stuck before and
you know it's it's influence influence
them the ability of the application to
be very performant so so so in ventually
we are doing it and and basically the
reason we're doing it is because we
created more and more layer eventually
this will give us what we believe need
which is to run one application the only
thing is that if one will take all this
layer and said wait can we actually take
all of this stack and just you know we
think about what we really need in order
to run it and you know clean it up you
know clean slate you probably will not
choose this architecture it is going to
work it's just not the right
it's not the best it's not the more
efficient one so you have said that in
our current model we are trading off
efficiency in favor of compatibility and
you've touched on this in this
conversation already but I really want
to give the listeners a better idea
describe what you mean by these
trade-offs between efficiency and
compatibility in more detail so what I
mean is that when you today want to run
an application you want to do to you
today on the current machine you know
the care about the system the carrier
machine you probably don't want to take
your operating system and run it on a I
don't know Pentium 110 years ago
Hardware right you probably don't want
to do that but if you will take right
now the distro an enormous operating
system that you want and you will try to
do that you will be successful you can
actually take right now I don't know
tabi and destroy like Ubuntu and put it
on ten years ago computer and the
question is why
so basically when we when we are
creating this evolution about let's go
and add more you know make make the
stack better to run one application with
the one user on a single server we
basically it was important to us that it
ordered to make it adoptable we will
support and all the old architecture and
when you're doing this this is fine but
then you basically cannot make it you
have some dependency and imitation you
cannot do it the best or the most
efficient that you can so what I'm
saying is that we make you know the
community of top artists is to basically
make a choice and the choice that they
make is that it's much more important to
them to run you know to support all the
old architecture probably because it's
easier to make it adoptable that way
then to actually you know start with a
clean slate and said what do we really
need that's what I meant I mean maybe
the best part will be let's just think
about what we really need in order to
run the application of today because you
know the requirement change
so in what ways does the Linux kernel
have excess complexity as we've built up
these additional abstractions as we've
built up this additional compatibility
where are the most pertinent places
where we have excess complexity so the
first thing so so first let let's
separate between the operating system
itself and the layer that we put on top
of it right
the caramely itself has a lot of fun
necessary for instance driver that you
can run with right if you go in today
and you're running on the cloud you
cannot go to the machine you're still
going to have a USB driver and the same
thing with floppy no one is using floppy
it's going to be there and there's a lot
of other example of stuff that you don't
really need maybe run an application
that's not even using the network is
still going to run the network driver or
you don't need a volume is still going
to have the volume driver so basically
what I'm saying is that you have a lot
of stuff that honest are necessary this
is the first complexity because you know
this is lines of code that you need to
maintain that you make sure that it's
working and supported the other thing if
you have all of this line of code and
complexity for instance before when you
were running you ran on this big
machines
therefore you add more than one user and
because of that you need to make sure
that you check it there is a permission
check right you need to make sure that
me as a user are not doing any harm to
your application that's again not
necessary if you only run one user and
in the cloud today that's what we're
doing we don't really you know running
the application did you know you could
have a multi users on the application
itself but we don't really care on the
level of you know the operating system
itself and actually it's also not secure
I preferred that no one will be able to
actually SSH your machine it's dangerous
so so that's another thing or the
permission check it's also you know it's
it's taking your promo into your app
performance down right because the
operating system actually need to check
before it's doing something you define
what a permission check is for those who
don't know yeah permission check means
basically another question of so you
have a tab so there is a few things
first of all permission your check is
who is this user right and second of all
there is two layers on top rata system
one of them is
what called kernel mode in user mode
when I'm running application I'm gonna
get an a on in a user mode and the only
thing that is running on the camera it's
basically the operating system itself
the kernel itself so if I'm making a
call in my operating system what will
happen on my on my application usually I
will have some libraries that I'm going
to use that will make what call an you
know an API call to the operating system
when that will happen it will go to a
kernel mode right basically the current
the kernel would catch it and said is
that okay are you writing to a place
that I'm okay with to write it is that
not violate any of the permission check
maybe he's right into a place when there
is either another application using in
this memory right so just make sure that
this is a safe call so that's one thing
that I mean so first of all with the
user and second of all make sure to
separate between user and between
application and user does that make
sense yeah yeah absolutely so explain
why this model of permission checks is
somewhat outdated and why it penalizes
us so much mainly it's not needed right
now if I'm using and I'm running as we
said in the beginning the purpose is to
run one application so doesn't have to
have a virtual space address because
there was only one application this is
you know the memo is what we have and
therefore there is no you know there's
no going to be any problem with a page
fault and that's it because again you
don't care because you only run your
application that's the only thing on
your machine if you're the only user of
course you allowed to do this stuff
you're running on privilege mode there
is no one else you know you are the only
person in the machine and this is your
application you can do whatever you want
so there is a lot of a lot of just
unnecessary it's not that there it's you
know it's very very complicated but it's
unnecessary and that's taking a CPU
cycle and so on that you really don't
need to waste so what is a unit kernel
how can we move this conversation
towards a discussion of you know kernels
so the idea with the only color is just
a change approach right what we said is
that until now we went into the
evolution and we looked at what happened
created this enormous stack
what unique and poor saying let's start
from the from the top let's understand
what we really need to run so you're
taking your application and now the
question is what your application will
in it so what libraries it's using which
driver is using whether you run are you
running on this hypervisor and data a
provider you're running in the cloud all
of these questions are important because
to be fair I don't need this machine all
the drivers I only need the driver that
actually will be used so what they did
they basically come to a different
approach and they said here's my
application in the you know only the
libraries that I do is all the driver
that I need and that's it not package it
and make it a virtual machine or a
bootable image right so that's basically
that it's a different port and now
suddenly from having a destroy I don't
know like the deviance role I stay
locked was a 419 million line of code
suddenly you have I don't know a very
small one like two thousand line of code
and when you have that now it's very
very easy right the performance is very
very good but also it's very easy to
understand what's going on very easy to
work on very easy to maintain so so
that's that's the benefit of it but it's
doing the same thing right in the end of
the day running one application in the
cloud and everybody is using it this is
like that simple right when we strip
away those 400 million lines of code
that we don't need and we were left with
the two thousand lines of code what are
the things that we always need what are
the aspects of that Linux kernel that
we're always going to need even though
we're running in a unit kernel so the
first thing that you need is the driver
itself right because that's what we will
talk to your hardware so you need to
know that so again only the drivers that
you can end if you don't need network
you will not have a network drivers the
second thing that you need you need
something to package it and manage it
that that's for instance right in you
look at something like crampon that's
what they're doing it's basically
another like Clara that will you know
manage that which is again can be very
thin because there is not a lot to
manage now and then on top of it you
have to have your libraries that your
application is right so if the Lipsy or
something else you need basically they
you know the the libraries that your
application code is using and then you
need
application called application runtime
of course but but that's it that's all
you need you don't need much more than
this so is a eunuch Colonel still
considered an operating system it's an
operating system ring in a way it's a
kernel right and it's people like to say
that the eunuch kernel is the
application so but in the end of the day
I'll operate this is if something does
manage it and it is been minute right I
mean to someone something could manage
it it's just a very very lightweight
operate the system so my application is
always going to need these certain
specific things like specific language
runtimes specific hardware drivers how
do I determine which of these is going
to go in to my unit kernel if so in
terms of the driver you need to know
where you're running on for instance I'm
running on the Zen so we'll need the
driver then I'm running go and I don't
know when Google compute engine so I
know that what they have is basically
KPM so I'm gonna let those drivers one
morning gonna exercise we need these
drivers oh I'm running with bare metal
Raspberry Pi it doesn't matter what you
need the driver for that so that's
something that usually it's something
that the user need to do before we
created our project person need to
understand I want to run there this is
the driver that I need and you need to
give them besides that there is the you
know the wrapper itself and that's been
given by it's called like for instance
ramp kernel it's called ramp run I mean
this is the tool that doing this magic
and it's also and and so so that's in in
a for instance in front part but there
is added like you know it's me it's
called something else and in marathi
hook or something else but the idea that
there is something that you know how to
build and what is doing is basically
package it with your compiler so in the
end of the day what you running is
binary so if you wanted to compile
application for whatever python for
instance in the end of the day what to
take what library to take from the phyto
and that's the compiler of python or to
know to do so at the end of the day
we'll take what the compiler is given
which is a binary plus the basic
libraries that you need wrapped with the
container everyday driver
that's what you get in the end of the
day we're getting the unica itself okay
so I I specify the things that my unit
Colonel is going to need what so what is
the process describe the process in more
detail of how after I specify you know
the aspects of the library operating
system that my unit colonel needs how
does that get transitioned into a unit
colonel that I can run so I mean I can
go with you as much as detailed as I can
but there it is that there is tools for
it so you don't really do the artwork so
what you're doing is you're running some
command call like for instance in
varieties if you had a normal riot
compile and then are you giving the
drivers that you need it's like a
command tools that you're doing and the
magic itself is done in these tools and
to be fair this is not something that
either me or my team do well maybe we
created some you know we modify those
tool but the tool itself is not created
by my team Oh me so talking a little bit
more about how unicorns actually work a
eunuch Arnall runs in a single address
space what does that mean it's mean that
so let's say right now let's take it one
second to the regular colonel let's say
that right now I have two processes
running okay and I have one memory right
so I can do a lot of manipulation with
it what does it mean maybe because the
process is going to do a lot of context
switch what I can do is is basically one
more application that eaten more
processes that each of them think that
they're getting the real virtual machine
visual memory but actually I'm managing
some some table that reference me to you
one where and and I'm only giving them
what they really use so what does it
mean it means that if I have two
processes and right now I'm running on
one process and I have memo I don't know
the amount of the memory that I have it
acts it doesn't matter I can take
another process and make him think that
is using the same memory and here's all
the memory that in it but actually
that's not really true what I'm doing is
that if I need to give it back to him I
can either
you know I can I'm managing basically
the address himself this is are talking
an irregular machine in unit count of
you have only one processes so therefore
all these cell table or father is going
and you just donated it all the pages
and so on it's just don't need it so
therefore you have one memory the memory
is a physical memory and that process is
what is using it and that's it I mean
he's will be getting all of it does that
make sense yeah totally so our unit
kernels better suited to small single
purpose servers like DNS for example or
could you fit an entire rails app in a
unit kernel so you can you can fit
everything in unique and in the end of
the day it's only your binary rocket
right so you can take I don't know and
all application and as long as this
application is not and not doing
anything that unity owner is not support
you can do that you know the question if
it makes sense to do that that's a
different one but I think that what cool
about única now is the fact that it's
the boot time is very fast therefore
usually you will find a lot of use case
like in NFV word for instance aim which
is basically a server less function so
like there's something that I want to
run it's very very small I wanted to run
only when user calling it so because
it's very very fast for me to boot the
unique and I'll I will do that and then
we'll kill it immediately so for
instance under will be probably really
really good implementation it can't be
implemented by UN Akana yeah maybe you
could talk about that in a little more
detail so you know lambda is closely
aligned with this idea of serverless
architecture explain what lambda is and
why that makes sense in the context of
you know kernels so so the idea with a
so today let's say you have an
application you run you need to run to
read to write all your lines you need to
manage those you need to write an API
for it for someone to et server and a
lot of management that you need to do
and sometimes and give you usually you
need to either package it is in
container and deploy it on a machine but
a lot of the time you
the only thing you want is something
very simple you want to run a very small
function and this function is really not
doing much I don't know let's say that
every time that someone is putting
something in s3 I want to run something
yeah I want to need to actually manage
the server here they really need to
actually take a VM put on the right
patch if my application and everything
that I need create an API and so on
maybe not right because it's kind of
simple so what what AWS there were the
first that I know that it is actually I
run IO maybe before they might I'm not
sure but about the idea that you only
going to spin up this functionality when
you actually need it and when the user
is not going to a pathway they were not
going to have anything like your
infrastructure that it is running it
that's the ID so for instance you know
you want to put something every time
that someone is putting something in s3
so what I want is that only when someone
is going to put something in history
it's going to spin up an Android that
will run my container or única and do
something and then died right so that's
basically the idea with a and SS lambda
just don't manage your server anymore
we're going to do that for you
so let's talk about that in more detail
so if if I'm Amazon and I'm thinking
about how I want to vend this serverless
capability to my customers should I
architect it using unit kernels should I
use containers should I use some
combination of the two what would be the
different trade-offs in those different
architectural ways of them implementing
their serverless architecture so today
what are you doing is they're using a
container and what are you doing because
they want to spare the time of actually
spinning up the container they're
reusing container but unique and it can
be a very very good fit for it because
as I said it's very very fast boot it's
very light in terms of size and you know
if your function is if you know that
every time that someone is something
putting in s 2 you need to run the same
function so build the unica at one time
and then just use it whenever you want
it would be very fast to boot
and you're getting of course a lot of
security and right the benefit of
unicorn so I feel that that probably
would be a bit of a better approach but
I mean you know both of them will work
could you contrast them in more general
context so how does docker how do docker
containers compare to unit kernels so
the idea with docker container versus
unit so unique and uh first of all it's
usually a VM or bootable image dr.
Cutten are not right it needs to run on
some kernel the kernel is something that
you're sharing between all your
container what you do putting on the
docker container is all the dependency
of your application the libraries and
whatever you need to run in your leak
and you also need to put your drivers
right because it's basically running
directly on you know it's basically a VM
which in very very like well OS was
running you know directly they won't
hypervisor on their matter in in docker
you you need this kernel right you need
somehow to get this kernel so if you're
running on you know let's just compare
right if you're running an iPod visor
let's say I'm running on AWS Oh AWS run
exam so I have you know is then now I
can either run Yanik ml I can run
container if a morning your new kernel
basically I just running an operating
system of VM on top of is then very very
easy right I mean there is no I needed
necessary anything there if you wanna
get on container what you need to do is
to spin up some Linux machine or some
operating system and on top of it put
your container so basically you have an
operating system that you know the Linux
con tellin ox is a bit you know it's an
of each kernel it's all the kernel
getting all the drivers and everything
you can and then you put in the
container on top of it so that's the
only real problem right so you basically
have the problem of much mature
operating system versus a very light one
and also of course but but you know but
docker will put only the libraries the
tonight on on the application so so how
do the performance characteristics
differ between you know kernels and
docker containers because obviously you
know Carl's
fast spin up docker containers are fast
to spin up so are their performance
differences in terms of startup time and
are their performance differences in
terms of what's going on once the
container or unit kernel is actually
running yeah so the good never question
it to be how you running a container if
you're running the container or bare
metal on a very minimum Linux of course
there is less but think if you are alpha
just what most of the people are running
today is they are running but it on
hypervisor and therefore you're running
a professor in your advisor you have all
those Linux kernel right this is the end
of the data running one kernel and you
have all day you know the switches and
everything you know that the permission
check and all the stuff that we talked
about it before right the the page
falling on all of this and context
switch and then you have your your guest
operating system which is again it's
another kernel right and then on top of
it you put in your container so
basically you have two layer of kernel
right if you wanna give me Colonel again
it depends where you're running it if
you're running on an eye provider you
have only died professor and then a very
very very team operating system so
basically again it depends where you
running it in terms of performance you
know you have less layer oh it's better
performs in numbers again you can go and
see quite a lot of like for instance
include OS is a did an article about a
how their unit color is running based
and you can see huge difference then
regular VM and and even container it's
performed very very well again it
depends how many you layer you have in
the stack and this is your choice right
can you describe what happens when I
deploy my eunuch Erna against a
hypervisor not much use a VM you're
putting it up that's it nothing it's
like a regular VM you can do you could
take this and that's it okay could you
contrast it to what what would happen if
you deployed docker container against a
hypervisor yeah so in first you need to
install you know you need somehow to
deploy a machine if guest to us with
Carol right so I mean that's something
that will have to happen
and the colonel will be a full colonel
right it will be like with all the stuff
that we talk that it's really really not
necessary permission check and so on and
then you're going to put the docker
container right so in the docker
container and you will have the library
that you need so in the end of the day
you have another layer there which have
a full Linux kernel which you don't
really need it you don't have to have I
understand okay so I want to talk about
what changes once we have unit kernels
so once we've removed all of these
permission checks how does our world
change how what speeds up what are the
advantages that we are getting
so basically operating system is started
and then your application is running
immediately right and then it's your
application running on a kernel mode
which means that it's you know all the
code that you want to do is you can do
there is not a contact there this the
switch between the kernel and user mode
there is no a contest switch because
there's no other processes and there's
no fault page because there is not it's
one single space so so basically all
these unnecessary stuff is not happening
and what really happening is that your
application is running is using whatever
it need and that's it I mean it's very
simple and since the eunich are can run
directly on the hypervisor or the
hardware without being in a virtualized
operating system does this mean that we
can pack
yuuna kernels more densely on this
underlying substrate than we would be
able to with virtualization so the thing
is like this let's say that right now
I'm creating a bootable image I can run
it directly on the bare metal machine
but usually in bare metal machine I have
a lot of resource the beauty of única is
that you don't need those resource right
they are very very small unicorn right
they're very very small so you will not
want to waste all this huge server that
you bought so therefore it doesn't
really make to run it to run into
directly on bare metal without some
hypervisor
but if you want to get on internet of
things even dead embedded device now it
actually makes sense because first of
all
there is not a lot of space and space
are very very important and you want to
give the space to your application for
real and not to your operating system so
let's make a lot of sense right and so
so as I said it makes a lot of sense and
in this world of internet of things but
then what we what we doing for instance
is we're making sure that the only
ground we run directly on there on them
by the device right there is no I
provider there's not another layer it's
like you know it's stream down there a
embedded device but if you wanna engage
the said server in the cloud that will
argue that you probably want to put so
my provider because otherwise you're
wasting a lot of resource so is there a
particular type of hypervisor that the
unit kernel typically runs on so there
so when we started this process most of
the most of the unicameral started in
project would call mini OS which is
coming from a Zen but since then you
know we help and a lot of other and edit
support for a lot others so right now
first and specifically we are supporting
in in a exercise which is the vSphere
environment of being where and we're
supporting a Zen supported KVM and qmu
so basically you can run on everywhere I
mean the only thing that we are not
working on yak is iPhone V and the
reason is because it's window space so I
need to go so so we need to figure out
what to do there but yeah everyone it
does it matter are there advantages that
particular hypervisors can give to the
unit kernel running on it I don't really
think I mean I think that in the end of
the day it's a VM so the IP for the
hypervisor it's a VM
there's no busy yeah okay as I said they
think that I think that it's very very
important to the VM to the unicorn
itself is the fact that you're getting
performance of container right because
it's very it's even fast sometimes it's
fast to boot it then a regular container
but you're getting the maturity of VM
which is great right because you're
getting the security of the VM and all
the management that all those eyeballs
are giving you for years so I think that
that you know that make it a very strong
case and also people doesn't need to
change anything in their environment
which I flow it's very strong
most of the people that running today
running on hypervisor
they're a data center right so you you
mentioned security what are the security
vulnerabilities of the Linux kernel that
yoona kernels can help give us a better
model to deal with so I was lucky that
the only one is that because there was a
big Linux kernel it's a lot of line it's
a lot of functionality therefore there
is a lot of point that you can penetrate
to it right and I think that this is the
scariest thing right I mean you can SSH
to it you can run you know you can try
to mimic different drivers to create a
lot of the mess on there is a lot of
stuff that you can do there that it's
very very dangerous
so by stripping down the operating
system and taking out stuff like SSH and
so on capability you're basically
limiting the surface of attack and I
like to look at it you know like like a
good exam example that I like to give
it's like it's like basically a house
with windows in the door and you're
locking though right so it's kind of sad
but people can still penetrate versus a
room without Doorn in a window so it's
very hard to penetrate so that's the
difference between unicorn and a regular
Linux quite the system I have read also
that there are certain security
vulnerabilities that might be picked up
if you are using a unit kernel for
example because the application is
running in the same address space as the
kernel there's potentially buffer
overflow vulnerabilities is this a
realistic problem so I mean this is
funny because we had a long discussion
discussion about it to try to understand
what exactly you know the formality I
feel that what people need to understand
is that eventually your unicorn law is
basically a VM that's running only one
application and it disciplic Asian
someone managed to somehow get to the
Uni kernel and sabotage it
the other
Cashin is not going to work and the
machine is not going to work and I don't
care because I mean I do care and I will
need to fix it and spin up a new one but
it's not that I'm attached to the
specific OS it's not that I have to go
and figure out what's going on because
nothing will be affected except this
process and a lot of day security work
that been done in linux is around the
fact that usually you have more than one
processes and you need to make sure that
if one of them and it's somehow to
sabotage and get to kernel mode and not
do a lot of damage it will not hurt the
other and therefore you need to do the
separation between the modes and so on
that's not a clippable for unicolor
because there is only one one process
therefore if these forces is you know if
this unique kernel is dead it's dead
there it's not sanitized any other
application that's running somewhere
else and I think this is the beauty of
it so what are the types of problems in
in the traditional Linux kernel if you
had access to the complete address space
by way of this buffer overflow
vulnerability and if you had the
complete Linux kernel how would that
contrast with the situation that you
just described where in the eunuch urn
'el if you can have access to the entire
address space you know you're saying it
doesn't actually matter because the the
eunuch are so restricted in its
functionality could you contrast that
why is that why is it a problem in the
full Linux kernel and it's not a problem
in unit kernels so so let's look what we
can do is an exercise we understand what
is in the Linux kernel actually
protective okay so the first thing that
there is is like privilege separation
right but again there is no need here
because there is only one process
running so you don't need to say oh you
know there's no point right what what is
to separate the setting the second thing
that will be is the protection of the
Rings right but again there is one one
of the occasions so even if this
application for some reason will try to
do something with very malicious to the
VM itself the machine will die but again
it's not going to affect anybody if
you're looking at our protected memory
space so again because you
you know there's only one process that
run against a the eunuch colonel and
there is no only one single address
space right so memory space protection
guard like virtual process a you know
process address space from another
process there is no again with only one
process there is no need for this
isolation it's not really and isolation
that it's capable that it's needed if
you're looking at the namespaces again
it's the same thing it's like there's
single process it doesn't make any sense
if there is a fine grain of access
control like sed knocks again it's the
same thing like the number one one
doesn't make much much sense but what I
will argue is that if someone will go
inside and will manage to run a buffer
overflow the results would be exactly
like the results in a regular VM but
it's not going to be worse than this
okay you lose the machine which means
that you lose the application but you
know what you have only one application
running on it so at least none none of
the other got it back then again like we
can continue ongoing but basically
application execution enforcement again
I mean it just doesn't make sense when
you're looking at one forces running in
one machine all of these things that
they the kernel is giving you it's just
not needed when you're running only one
process on one space space that make
sense yeah absolutely
so we'll do you think public clouds like
AWS or Google compute are they gonna
host unit kernels how could you see that
that happening so that a great question
so today if I'm running an AWS and we
are right I mean you specifically the
tool that we created called unique is
running an AWS is supporting it but we
are limited because when we wanted to
actually add the machine itself the
bootable image to an instant the minimum
that we can get is one gig this is like
the minimum that you can get by AWS
therefore if I can run something like 50
to Meg I'm still need to pay for one gig
doesn't really make sense so so AWS is
not right now the best cloud to run your
new kernel there's other cloud that mom
excites are thinking infra member
correctly in Google there is two way you
can do it either
like this
you know fixed-price base side or you
can do it you know more like custom emc
has a cloud that called virtual stream
that there they have like a pattern of
something that called micro vm which is
basically you paying only for what
you're using so it's okay you can but
but you know I'm assuming that women
will be more popular they will adjust
their this the price they will have to
so so I'm believe that in the future it
will be more make sense today probably
if you will run on premise to be more
usable so you mentioned unique let's
talk a little bit more about that what
is unique so unique is basically you
remember that we talked about are you
actually building your neck Hana so I
described a little bit and of course I
abstract it right I didn't tell you all
the details because it's too complicated
but in the end of the day the bottom
line is that it's complicated and what
we wanted to make sure is that if there
is a user that understand that he has an
application and you want to run it and
you understand that it's you know
unicorn or maybe it's a better fit for
his application I don't know because you
want a space to you know because it's
more secure because it's taking like
space because it's very performed well
what we wanted to make sure is that it
would be very very easy for him to do
that because not everybody that writing
application running you know I don't
know a website and the standing up to
compile a driver's so the idea with
unique was let's do what doctor did to
Linux container and just make it very
easy to work with so if someone would
want to go and take his application
running in container today it's not that
hard to do it with docker we wanted to
give him the some experience to run it
in única and we felt felt that if if we
will do that people will use it because
as i said i would be believer that this
is daletech show of the future cloud and
internet of things so how do developers
actually turn their applications into
you know kernels today how does that
contrast with how you aspire unique to
work so how it's happening without doing
it go always up and in with unique both
questions how does it contrast in unique
with what's happening to
so though the work that we did it's kind
of a complicated right we wanted to run
it on the exercise you need to figure
out which driver is working on it this
is not an easy work right I mean this
work for instance been done by Falco
Harvey and these guys like you know
that's what he knows he's compiled you
know I think debugging can simply cut in
crazy stuff right and what it is
basically you know you need to
understand which driver you will really
need there so our luck was that ramp
you're not specifically for instance is
based on a FreeBSD so if there is a if
something like exercise support FreeBSD
we can actually go and kind of use those
computers a hope that you will take
those drivers that already been done for
FreeBSD it will work for forum so we did
a lot of work on this but it's not
always working you need to figure out
but missing and which driver is depends
on which driver so it's a lot of work
that we did right after we did this work
now we know how to do something like
that
so what we did we basically automated
that we say that those people think
that's your code we will make sure that
you know we tell us which provider you
want to run in and we're going to
compile your code on the language that
you choose with the drivers that you
need and will create your bootable image
so you will not you know we're
obstructing all of this from you but
this is not an easy work I mean we
worked on it quite a lot yeah there's
been a lot written about you know how
challenging it's been for docker to get
darker compatibility on Windows and Mac
and everywhere is it sounds like with
unique it's essentially paradigmatically
the same sort of challenge where you
really have to get compatibility with
all these different hardware systems all
these different cloud providers all
these different types of unit kernels
how do you address that compatibility
how do you manage that work that
workload so so actually when we wrote
your name the instruction that hired to
the team is we have to make it very very
pluggable because we don't really as he
said right there is a lot povo
a lot of provided that we wanted to
support there is a lot of unique another
who wanted to support there's a lot of
unique and provide special provided that
we wanted to support and to be fair this
is
such a green area that we don't know
what's going to win maybe Mirage may be
wrong maybe it was we don't know right
and therefore we decided not to choose
right and what we did we basically set
built up unique to be very very
pluggable so we've been inspired by the
kubernetes architecture and what we did
we basically build you know so we kind
of like created an interface to have
providers and interface to a compiler so
now if you bring me your code there is
two thing that I need to know hey you
know what type of code is like I don't
know you want to run go number two is
which unicolor you want to run it on so
either wrap or include OS or whatever
you want to run on Mirage and then the
last one is which provider you want to
run it because for instance maybe you
want to run this unicorn on Zen or maybe
you want to run it on AWS which is also
Zen so that will be the compiler but the
provider will be AWS right because when
we talk into the API we will talk to AWS
we will not talk to a rackety to Zen so
we build it like this that's right now
if we wanted to add support for
something else and a good example is
probably is include alas so included is
so unique and read some article on it
and they really they said outcome
included us is not one of this unique
kernel that you support so we they just
added support for it so you know as I
said it and it was quite easy for them
because what they needed to do is a
container that will run the compiled
itself and that's it because we already
have the support for qmu and they
individual box that they needed as a
provider so you know it's very easy to
do that if you know what to do so so
again but but um
yeah I mean as I said if you look at the
coding unique and we see active
abilities you see that it's very easy to
extend it like it's very easy to add
more support wider are we doing it we
didn't constantly right now we're
working on a more and more support so
when you talk about rump versus Mirage
could you explain what the difference
between those two are like what is rump
what is Mirage and you frame it as if
it's as if one of these is going to win
explain what you mean by that
so I mean there is a thread of here
right ROM Ryan it's basically a eunuch
you know that kind of supporting quasi
compliance that means that if your
application is running and you know and
certify to run on plastic it will work
therefore it's mean that I can take C++
applications that you wrote or go or
anything out of you know nodejs or every
other language that you choose and it's
basically I don't need to modify the
language itself or the code that you
wrote in order to run it on ramp in my
budget it will be different because if
you look at include OS for instance
include OS the reason it's calling cool
device is because you need to do include
OS to your code to the C++ code which
means that they using a little bit
different libraries that are not not the
regular application is using if you're
running on Linux and therefore why I'm
but it means that you will need to
modify your application but because they
build it specifically and it's not
possible you can get a better
performance so it's basically a
trade-off if you will run your
application in your karma which is the
language that Mirage today so forth you
probably will get a better performance
but we need to run off karma when you
and you know not a lot of the
application today is running a comma so
it's a good question based you know what
people will prefer I'll be believer that
people will prefer one because it's you
know they don't need to modify the code
versus Miraj but there is a lot of
community around barrage less about ROM
so I'm believe that eventually maybe you
know my right is going to work on adding
more support well for stuff so maybe
we'll see I don't know great well indeed
where can people find out more about
unicorns and about you and your work so
if you're going to our get up so so my
team is doing a lot of stuff but that's
one of the things that we did if you're
going to the get up
EMC - advanced - dev you can see their
project call unique this is where you're
going to find the unique code and you
can install it and run it so it's very
very simple and beautiful our emails are
there so they can reach out to us you
can reach out me at twitter which is it
did idat and the skull of in hell
any yeah and I mean you will find me
just Google me hey why is it why is EMC
focused on unicron's you work at EMC
what is the business value there so so
so many before that I need to explain a
little bit so I'm working in EMC and I'm
the CTO of the cloud management division
we basically changing the way MCS trying
to think right so we have some people
call EMC told yo we doing programming
testing and development the what would
will be different we focusing a lot in
cloud foundry and other tools inside
this group I have a I pick two
developers to work directly for me and
we doing advanced development so this
project unique is coming from that so
it's a you vodka hobby that I mentioned
before in Scott Weis and myself are the
one who's responsible for your neck it
started as a defense developer project
but to be fair it just succeed more than
we expected we actually knew that it
will succeed but more than EMC maybe
thought that it will expect that and now
there is a lot of fuscus that we can
think of the TMC can leverage that but
the main focus was a to change
perception right
EMC as an innovative company I was doing
you know that is Edward with docker and
other companies and and besides that you
know this is a coconut technology and
this is what we're knotted to lead so so
again that's it there is no really
business value right now but I believe
that like paste after we did it we
discovered that there is a lot of
options to put it inside EMC EMC a
product to put it inside so there is a
lot of option that we see sure to
leverage that absolutely okay well a
deep thanks for coming on the show it's
been a real pleasure talking to you
thank you so much for having me
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio name to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]